Language [English](#) [Māori](https://www.parliament.nz/mi/pb/sc/make-a-submission/document/54SCPRIP_SCF_9608F1D1-2216-4292-C788-08DC90C80755/climate-change-response-emissions-trading-scheme-agricultural/)

Search [Advanced Search](https://www.parliament.nz/en/search)

 Search

Search

 Search

Language [English](#) [Māori](https://www.parliament.nz/mi/pb/sc/make-a-submission/document/54SCPRIP_SCF_9608F1D1-2216-4292-C788-08DC90C80755/climate-change-response-emissions-trading-scheme-agricultural/)

    In the 54th New Zealand Parliament there are 6 parliamentary parties represented by 123 MPs. These MPs represent 65 general electorate seats and 7 Māori electorates. The other 51 MPs are selected from the party lists.

    Parliament's decisions affect all New Zealanders. Have your say and influence the laws passed by Parliament. You can get involved by voting in elections, contacting an MP,  making a submission or petitioning Parliament.

    #### Parliament Buildings’ street address
    
    [Parliament Buildings  
    Molesworth Street  
    Wellington 6160  
    New Zealand](http://maps.google.com/?q=Wellington+Parliament+Pipitea+Wellington+6011)
    
    [

    For more information about tours and visiting Parliament, click here.](https://www.parliament.nz/en/visit-and-learn/visit/)

[

The House next meets on Tuesday, 15 October 2024](https://www.parliament.nz/en/pb/meetings-of-parliament/)

### Listen

There is no current live audio feed.

[

The House next meets on Tuesday, 15 October 2024](https://www.parliament.nz/en/pb/meetings-of-parliament/)

### Listen

There is no current live audio feed.

Privacy
=======

1. [Home](https://www.parliament.nz/en/)
2. [Footer](https://www.parliament.nz/en/footer/)
3. [Privacy](https://www.parliament.nz/en/footer/privacy/)

**Originally published:** 12 October 2015

**Last updated:** 22 May 2019

**Organisation Privacy Statement**
----------------------------------

New Zealand Parliament may collect personal data from you when you engage with us via telephone, fax, written letter, or digital channels such as email or website forms. Details on the collection and use of your personal data via digital channels are explained in the Website Privacy Statement on this page. 

### Personal information collected by telephone

We record inbound calls made to our Parliament main line numbers, 0800 7273 6282 and 04 817 9999.

For calls to these numbers, recording starts once your call is answered by a Customer Service Representative. Any wait time prior to your call being answered is not recorded. The phone number you have called from is also stored so we can retrieve the call recording in the future. We do not use your phone number for any other purpose.

Recording automatically stops when you are transferred to anyone outside our Customer Service Team, or when the call is terminated.

Call recordings are stored securely for up to 30 days, after which they are automatically deleted.

**Website Privacy Statement**
-----------------------------

This privacy statement applies to your personal information collected on the New Zealand Parliament website [www.parliament.nz](http://www.parliament.nz/)

The information in this statement does not apply to any personal information collected by external websites the Parliament website redirects users to, including the external jobs listing website (livehire.com). For privacy information on an external website please refer to their privacy policy.

### Information on this site

The Parliament website provides information for the benefit of the public. The Office of the Clerk of the House of Representatives and the Parliamentary Service monitor the quality of the information available and update the information regularly.

### Maintenance of this site

The Parliamentary Service maintains and supports the infrastructure required to operate the website. Both the Office of the Clerk of the House of Representatives and the Parliamentary Service share the website for public communication purposes, therefore both agencies collect and hold any personal information received.

Both organisations are located at the following address:

Parliament Buildings  
Molesworth Street  
Wellington

### Security of information

Both our organisations take information security seriously. Our systems, including the information you provide us by email, through our website and by other methods, are monitored for security purposes so your communications may be seen by third parties as part of that cyber security monitoring.  This monitoring increases the likelihood that your information and parliamentary information systems are kept safe.

### Collection of personal information

You may browse and access information contained within our website without providing personal information.

There are some places on the website where you can choose to give your personal information to the Office of the Clerk and the Parliamentary Service (“us”, “we”), such as using the online form for select committee submissions, contacting us by email, Rich Site Summary (RSS) feeds or online newsletter subscriptions. In these cases we collect the following personal information from you:

* Your name, your contact details and text or documents submitted when you make an online submission to a select committee. We collect contact information so that we can communicate with you about the submission process. (Refer additional information on making a submission below).
* Email addresses and email content collected when you send an email directly from the Parliament website contact links.
* Email addresses through subscribing to RSS feeds and subscription newsletters. 

### Use and disclosure of personal information

We manage or use the above information in the following ways:

**Contact information** collected through online submissions is kept separately from all Select Committee official records.  The contact details collected from the submission process are not published unless they are contained within the submission text.  Contact information collected from online submissions is archived and retained in accordance with the Public Records Act 2005 when the item of business the submission is associated with is closed.  You may request access to and correction of your contact information at any time.  Your contact information will not be disclosed to third parties, except where authorised by law. See below for additional information about submissions.

**Email addresses and email content** is collected when you send an email to an @parliament.govt.nz email address from the parliament website.  Email addresses and email content will be used for the purpose for which they were provided and will not be disclosed to any other parties, except where authorised by law.  Emails are archived and retained in accordance with the Public Records Act 2005. 

**RSS feeds and subscription newsletters** require us to collect your email address and/or your IP address so that we can provide the service you have requested through the parliament website.  RSS feeds tell you what’s new on the parliament website and RSS feeds provide summary information for a particular web page directly to your browser’s toolbar.  The subscription newsletter(s) will be emailed directly to your email address.  You can unsubscribe from RSS feeds and newsletter subscriptions at any time.

### Statistical information and cookies

Some information is automatically retrieved about your visit to our site, however no effort is made to identify individual users. The information that may be retrieved includes:

* your IP address
* the search terms you used
* the pages you accessed on the website and the links you clicked on
* the date and time you visited the site
* the referring site (if any) through which you clicked through to this site
* your operating system (e.g., Windows or Mac)
* the type of web browser you use (e.g. Internet Explorer, Mozilla Firefox)
* other data like your screen resolution and the language setting of your browser.

The statistical information referred to above will be viewable by certain Parliamentary Service and Office of the Clerk staff, contractors or third parties who provide administration and/or improvements services in relation to the website. The information is used to produce summary reports which help us improve the website’s content and functionality.

Cookies are collected so that we may provide you with a better web service. They are only used to produce website statistics, personal information is not presented in any statistics produced. You can disable them or clear them out of your web browser without affecting your ability to use the site.

### Access to and correction of personal information

You have the right to ask for a copy of any personal information we hold about you, and to ask for it to be corrected if you think it is wrong. If you’d like to ask for a copy of your information, or have it corrected, please contact us in writing at:

Privacy Officer  
Office of the Clerk of the House of Representatives  
Private Bag 18041  
Parliament Buildings  
Wellington 6160

Email: [parliament.website@parliament.govt.nz](mailto:parliament.website@parliament.govt.nz)

### Application of the Privacy Act 2020

Personal information held by the Office of the Clerk is subject to the requirements of the Privacy Act 2020. The Parliamentary Service is only subject to the Privacy Act 2020 in relation to personal information that it holds about its employees and former employees. However, the Parliamentary Service has developed specific policies to address the release of information. Under these policies data collected will not be disclosed to a third party, unless such disclosure is authorised by law.

### Additional information on making a submission to a select committee

All submissions received by select committees either electronically, through postal services or any other channel will be published to the Parliament website.

Your submission will only be used for the item of business that it is submitted for. Once released, submissions are published to the parliament website. 

It is important that you separate your personal details from the main body of your submission, otherwise your personal details will not only be released publicly; they will also be published on the Parliament website. If you do wish to include any information of a private or personal nature in a submission, you should first discuss it with the Clerk of the committee to which you are submitting.

Contact the Clerk of Committee:  
Telephone: +64 4 817 9520[](# "Call: +64 4 817 9520")  
Email: [select.committees@parliament.govt.nz](mailto:select.committees@parliament.govt.nz)

##### Share

[Footer](https://www.parliament.nz/en/footer/) Also in this section:

* [Parliamentary Service and Office of the Clerk Responsible Disclosure](https://www.parliament.nz/en/footer/parliamentary-service-and-office-of-the-clerk-responsible-disclosure/)
